A Guide to the Population Council records, Population in Development Planning Program, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 15 FA1435
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Population in Development Planning Program, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 15
1971-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
FA1435
1.41 Cubic Feet 3 legal-size document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
Arrangement
Original order is maintained, as received. The records are loosely organized alphabetically by country.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Population Development Planning Program are primarily comprised of project administration files, as well as a small selection of program and policy planning and proposal documents. The project files often include correspondence, memos, progress reports, status and trip reports, and governing documents.
- Population in Development Planning Program, 1971-1977; 15
  - General - Program Statements, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General - Reports of Program, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General - Budgets, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General - Special Funding - AID, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Correspondence, Memos, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Staff Development Awards, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Status Report, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Reports, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Visting Personnel-Consultants, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bangladesh Institute of Development Studies (BIDS) - Research on Nutrition, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dominican Republic, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Institute of Social and Economic Change - Bangalore, India, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - BAPPENAS - Indonesia - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Central Bureau of Statistics (BPS) - Indonesia - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Governing Documents, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Visiting Personnel-Consultants, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Staff Development Awards, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - LEKNAS - Indonesia - Research on Regional Development and Migration, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lembaga Demografi - Indonesia - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - University of Nairobi - Kenya - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - University of Nairobi - Kenya - Governing Documents, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Korea Development Institute - Korea - Correspondence, Memos, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - KIFP - Korea - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Economic Planning Unit (EPU) - Malaysia - Correspondence, Memos, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - El Colegio de Mexico - Mexico - Governing Documents, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - University of Ibadan - Nigeria - Correspondence, Memos, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - University of Ife - Nigeria - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - University of Ife - Nigeria - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - University of Ife - Nigeria - Staff Development Awards, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - University of Lagos - Nigeria - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - University of Nigeria, Nsukha, Center for Demographic Research, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - OTEMO - Peru - Governing Documents, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - OTEMO - Peru - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - University of the Philippines - Correspondence, Memos (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - IDEP - Senegal - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Ministry of Planning (MSPL) - Sierra Leone - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC) - Sudan - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ministry of Economic Planning (MEP) - Sudan - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Ministry of Economic Planning (MEP) - Sudan - Visiting Personnel-Consultants, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - University of Gezira - Sudan - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - University of Khartoum, Center of Development Studies and Research (CDSR) - Correspondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - BRALUP - Tanzania - Governing Documents, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - BRALUP - Tanzania - Visiting Personnel-Consultants, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - BRALUP - Tanzania - Staff Development Awards, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Institute for Population Studies (IPS) - Thailand - Corrrespondence, Memos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Institute for Population Studies (IPS) - Thailand - Governing Documents, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Institute for Population Studies (IPS) - Thailand - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - National Economic and Social Development Board (NESDB) - Thailand, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - National Economic and Social Development Board (NESDB) - Thailand - Correspondence, Memos, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - National Economic and Social Development Board (NESDB) - Thailand - Governing Documents, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - National Economic and Social Development Board (NESDB) - Thailand - Reports, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - National Economic and Social Development Board (NESDB) - Thailand - Visiting Personnel-Consultants, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - University of Zambia, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 55)